A Guide to the The Personal Papers of Dorothea E. Abbott, 1950-1999
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
The Personal Papers of Dorothea E. Abbott, 1950-1999
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
RG 91
29 boxes.
Abbott, Dorothea E., 1921-1999
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Robert E. Abbott in 1999.
Biographical Information
Dorothea E. Abbott (1921-1999) was born in Queens County, New York, and attended Edison College in Fort Myers, Florida. She married Robert E. Abbott in 1943 and was an Arlington resident from about 1960 to 1995, when she moved to Hamilton, Ohio. A self-employed historian for over twenty years, Abbott wrote several books and numerous articles, including eleven for Arlington Historical Magazine. Article topics include the history of individuals, buildings, and localities in Virginia, especially Northern Virginia. She was active in the Arlington Historical Society and other civic groups and was one of the founders of the Arlington Heritage Alliance. At the time of her death she was preparing to write a book about Martha Washington.
Scope and Content
The personal papers described here are those collected and generated by Dorothea E. Abbott of Arlington, Virginia, in the course of her research about Arlington and other Virginia localities, Florida, Martha and George Washington, and other topics of interest to her. RG 91 is 12.1 linear feet.
The first six series include handwritten research notes, clippings, brochures, photographs, photocopies of newspaper and magazine articles, and drafts of her historical articles, 1950-1999. Additionally, there are numerous copies and transcripts of legal documents which originally date from the 18th through the 20th century. Most of them are copies from microfilm, and some are faded and difficult to decipher. By reading the files, researchers will be able to trace some of the sources she read in preparing her articles.
In Series 6, Northern Virginia Historical Groups, there are founding documents and early minutes for the Arlington Heritage Alliance, among other administrative records for Arlington- and Northern Virginia-based groups concerned with local history.
Arrangement
Record Group 91 is divided into six series: Series 1: Arlington and Northern Virginia Research Materials is arranged alphabetically by subject. Series 2: George and Martha Washington, contains series on publications, arranged alphabetically by title, and then notes and clippings, arranged alphabetically by subject. Series 3: Virginia Counties and Localities, Series 4: Florida Clippings, Notes, and Brochures, and Series 5: Miscellaneous Topics are all arranged alphabetically by subject. Series 6: Northern Virginia Historical Groups, have series arranged alphabetically by name of group.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
RG 175, Arlington Heritage Alliance, has the records of the AHA. RG 23, Personal Papers of Eleanor Lee Templeman, holds the historical research of another local historian and author.
Index Terms
Subjects:
History -- Research.; Virginia -- History; Arlington (Va.); Arlington County (Va.)
Contents List
- Arlington and Northern Virginia Research Materials
  - Abbey Mausoleum: Correspondence, Notes, Photographs, 1962 1962-1991 (Box 1)
  - Abbey Mausoleum: Legal Documents, 1900-1932 (1) (Box 1)
  - Abbey Mausoleum: Legal Documents, 1900-1932 (2) (Box 1)
  - Abbey Mausoleum: Clippings, 1984-1994 (Box 1)
  - Abbott-Horton Deeds, 1958, 1962, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Abingdon Park: Notes, Deeds, n.d., 1870-1875 (Box 1)
  - Abingdon Ruins: Correspondence, Notes, 1980-1991 (Box 1)
  - Abingdon Set-Aside: Legal Document and Abingdon Survey Notes, n.d., 1805 (Box 1)
  - Adams Family: Notes, Clippings, Deeds, Will, Photographs, n.d., 1780-1843, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Addison Family: Deeds, 1854-1856 (Box 1)
  - Alcova Heights: Clippings, 1969-1974, 1990, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Charles Alexander and Thomas Janney: Legal Documents, 1803, 1842 (Box 1)
  - Columbus Alexander Estate: Deeds, 1807-1914, 1938-1978 (1) (Box 1)
  - Columbus Alexander Estate: Deeds, 1807-1914, 1938-1978 (2) (Box 1)
  - Columbus Alexander Estate: Notes, Clippings (Box 1)
  - Mary Alexander, Langhorne, Huddleston: Notes (Box 1)
  - Richard Brown Alexander: Deeds, Notes, 1801-1834 (Box 1)
  - Alexander Family: Deeds, Clippings, Notes, 1946, 1981-1992 (Box 1)
  - Alexandria: Deeds, Notes, Photographs, 1858-1926, 1980s (Box 1)
  - Alexandria: Newsletters, Fact Sheets, Brochures, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
  - Alexandria: Clippings, n.d., 1968-1998 (1) (Box 2)
  - Alexandria: Clippings, n.d., 1968-1998 (2) (Box 2)
  - Alexandria: Clippings, n.d., 1968-1998 (3) (Box 2)
  - Alexandria Canal: Clippings, plat, 1882-1986 (Box 2)
  - Appalachian Trail Club Property Sale: Correspondence, Legal Documents, 1980-1994 (Box 2)
  - Archaeology: Northern Virginia: Photocopies, 1983-1988 (Box 2)
  - Arlington Architecture: Clippings, Brochures, 1994-1995 (Box 2)
  - Arlington Chestnut Oak Tree: Minutes, Notes, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Arlington County: "The Citizen," County Documents, Certificate of Incorporation, 1922-1923, 1984-1994 (Box 2)
  - Arlington County: Brochures, Maps, Photographs (Box 2)
  - Arlington County: Clippings, n.d., 1928, 1980-1996 (Box 3)
  - Arlington County: Clippings, n.d., 1928, 1980-1996 (Box 3)
  - Arlington Forest, Arna Valley, Ashton Heights: Clippings, 1985-1994 (Box 3)
  - Arlington Hall: Deeds, Maps, 1896-1962 (Box 3)
  - Arlington Hall: Notes, Correspondence, Reports, 1988-1989 (Box 3)
  - Arlington Hall: Clippings, Deeds, Maps, 1931-1993 (Box 3)
  - Arlington Museum: Clippings, Notes, 1981-1993 (Box 3)
  - Arlington National Cemetery: Clippings, Notes, Brochures, 1982-1996 (Box 3)
  - Arlington Radio Tower: Clippings, Notes, 1984-1987 (Box 3)
  - Arlington Turnpike: Legal Documents, n.d., 1852-1882 (Box 3)
  - Aubrey Family: Notes, Deeds, Report, n.d., 1733-1738 (Box 3)
  - Aurora Hills: Deeds, Notes, Maps, Clippings, 1874-1959 (Box 3)
  - Valorous G. Austin: Notes, Deeds, 1861-1869 (Box 3)
  - Bailey's Crossroads and Fairlington: Clippings, 1988-1990 (Box 3)
  - Frank Ball: Notes, Deeds, 1901-1926 (Box 3)
  - Ball Family: Notes and Deeds, n.d., 1865-1967 (Box 3)
  - Ball Family: Transcripts of Deeds, 1735-1864 (Box 3)
  - Ballston: Brochures, Newsletter, Photograph, 1988-1995 (Box 3)
  - Ballston: Clippings, 1984-1994 (Box 4)
  - Barker, Abram: Notes, Deeds, 1887-1907 (Box 4)
  - Bates-Ball-Lawrence: Notes (Box 4)
  - Birch: South Ballston: Deeds and Notes, 1885-1914, 1989 (Box 4)
  - Boulevard Manor: Clippings, 1990-1991 (Box 4)
  - Bradley, Charles S.: Notes, Deeds, 1891-1941 (Box 4)
  - James Brechin: Notes, Deeds (Box 4)
  - Bridges: Clippings, 1985-1994 (Box 4)
  - Broadwater to Hunter Deed, 1776 (Box 4)
  - Brookdale: 432 Acres: Notes, Deeds, 1859-1887 (Box 4)
  - E.B. Van Every Lot 12: Brookdale: Deeds, 1880-1945 (Box 4)
  - Brooks and Boswell: Deeds, 1945-1980 (Box 4)
  - Broyhill-Fort Bennett: Deeds, 1952-1953, 1979 (Box 4)
  - Calvert Family: Notes (Box 4)
  - Canals, Rivers, Boathouses, Newsletters, 1986-1993 (Box 4)
  - Carlin Family: Deeds, Clippings, Notes, Photographs, n.d., 1842-1975 (Box 4)
  - Causin, Cassin, Cassine, Casene Family: Notes, Article, Deeds, Correspondence, n.d., 1817-1941 (Box 4)
  - The Cedars: Correspondence, 1992 (Box 4)
  - The Cedars: Notes, Compositions, Deed, Photographs, Map, n.d., 1978 (Box 4)
  - Cemeteries: Newsletters, Reports, 1984-1994 (Box 4)
  - Chapman: Notes, Deeds, Articles, Correspondence, n.d., 1732-1983 (Box 4)
  - Cherrydale: Clippings, 1987-1995 (Box 4)
  - Church Histories: Brochures, Notes, Clippings, 1978-1993 (Box 5)
  - Churches in Northern Virginia: Notes, Deeds, n.d., 1879-1885 (Box 5)
  - Churches in Northern Virginia: Clippings, Deed, 1931, 1986-1994 (Box 5)
  - Civil War: Photocopies, Reprints, Correspondence, 1849, 1871-1880, 1977-1986 (Box 5)
  - Claremont: Clipping (Box 5)
  - Earl of Clarendon: Clippings, Notes (Box 5)
  - Clarendon: Deeds, Notes, 1897-1909 (Box 5)
  - Clarendon: Deeds, 1910-1918 (Box 5)
  - Clarendon: Notes, "The Roots of Clarendon," 1986 (Box 5)
  - Clarendon: Miscellaneous Reports, Notes, Photographs, 1989-1990 (Box 5)
  - Clarendon: Clippings, 1984-1995 (Box 5)
  - Clarendon United Methodist Church History: 1986-1992 (Box 5)
  - Colonial Village and Colonial Terrace: Clippings, 1981-1989 (Box 5)
  - Columbia Pike: Clippings, 1986-1992 (Box 5)
  - Columbia Turnpike: Legal Document: Transcript, 1847 (Box 5)
  - Columbus Country Club: Deeds, n.d., 1836-1925 (Box 6)
  - Corbett: Deeds, Notes, 1916-1973 (Box 6)
  - Courtlands and Court House: Clippings, Notes, Deed, 1923, 1988-1994 (Box 6)
  - Edward and Mary Crane: Legal Documents, 1895-1925 (Box 6)
  - Crystal City: Clippings, 1985-1994 (Box 6)
  - Dade Family: Correspondence, Notes, 1952-1992 (Box 6)
  - Dade Family: Clippings, Reports, Photographs (Box 6)
  - Dawson-Holymead: Deeds, 1863-1950 (Box 6)
  - Dawson-Holymead: Notes, Clippings, 1979-1990 (Box 6)
  - Dean Family: Notes, Clippings, Deeds, 1806-1836, 1985 (Box 6)
  - Deming, George: Deeds, 1894-1909 (Box 6)
  - William and James Donaldson: Deeds, 1745-1750 (Box 6)
  - Donaldson Family and Site: Report, notes, Clippings, Deeds, Photographs, n.d., 1860-1900 (Box 6)
  - Doubleday, Col. and Mrs. Charles W.: Deeds, Notes, Photos, Correspondence, Clippings, 1903-1993 (Box 6)
  - Doubleday Property: Notes (Box 6)
  - Douglas Park, Barcroft: Clippings, notes, 1900 (Box 6)
  - Douglas-Will-Lawrence: Deeds, 1836-1973 (Box 7)
  - Douglas-Will-Lawrence: Notes, Clippings, 1964-1994 (Box 7)
  - Dranesville: Brochure, Clipping, 1975 (Box 7)
  - Dueling Grounds Near Chain Bridge: Notes, Clippings, 1976-1981 (Box 7)
  - Early Land Records from 18th Century: Transcripts (Box 7)
  - Captain William Easby: Notes, Clippings, n.d., 1917 (Box 7)
  - East Falls Church: Clippings, Brochures, 1924, 1957, 1985-1994 (Box 7)
  - William Elliott and A.E. Elliott: Notes, Deeds, 1857-1886 (Box 7)
  - Emmert, George Hill, Jr.: Notes (Box 7)
  - Fairfax: Clippings Showing Old Photographs, 1989-1994 (Box 7)
  - Fairfax County Deed from Burroughs Family, 1938 (Box 7)
  - Fairlington: Clippings, 1991-1993 (Box 7)
  - Falls Church: Deeds, Brochures, n.d., 1908-1928 (Box 7)
  - Falls Church: Clippings, 1980-1994 (Box 7)
  - Fences: Clippings, 1989 (Box 7)
  - Fendall Family: Notes, Deed, n.d., 1803 (Box 7)
  - Fort F.C. Smith: Clippings, Newsletter, Notes, Invitation, 1987-1995 (Box 7)
  - Fort Myer and Fort Myer Heights: Clippings, 1981-1995 (Box 7)
  - Forts in Arlington: Clippings, Deed, 1837, 1960-1993 (Box 7)
  - Fostoria: Clipping, 1993 (Box 7)
  - Fraser-Childs: Notes (Box 7)
  - Frye, Jack-Hughes, Howard: Notes, Clippings, Correspondence, 1959-1996 (Box 7)
  - Furlong Family: Deeds, 1869, 1925-1965 (Box 7)
  - Furniture: Clippings, 1992-1993 (Box 7)
  - George Washington Parkway: Correspondence and Documents, 1936-1956 (Box 7)
  - George Washington Parkway: Clippings, Articles, Newsletters, 1936, 1956-1957, 1981-1992 (Box 7)
  - Gladwell Family: Letter, 1991 (Box 7)
  - Glencarlyn: Deed, Clippings, 1810, 1987-1988 (Box 8)
  - Graham, Philip, and Katharine-Frankfurter, Felix: Notes, Clippings, 1994 (Box 8)
  - Grand United Order of Odd Fellows-Frank Hume: Deed, Notes, 1884 (Box 8)
  - Grave Sites: Pictures, Notes, Clippings, n.d., 1982-1993 (Box 8)
  - Great Falls: Clippings, Brochures, 1984-1988 (Box 8)
  - Charles Green: Clippings, 1990 (Box 8)
  - Hamilton Homes, South Monroe: Deeds, 1938-1976 (Box 8)
  - Harlow-Richard-Wilkinson-Hunter: Notes, Correspondence, Deeds, 1919-1993 (Box 8)
  - Hayden Subdivision: Plats and Legal Documents, 1934-1950 (Box 8)
  - William Henson: Deeds, 1899-1925 (Box 8)
  - Highview Park: Clippings, 1989-1994 (Box 8)
  - Henry L. Holmes-Butler, Brookdale: Deeds, 1882-1930 (Box 8)
  - Hopkins Family: Notes, Deeds, n.d., 1782-1848 (Box 8)
  - Horse Racing: Clippings, 1989-1994 (Box 8)
  - Houses in Northern Virginia, including Sears Houses: Notes, Articles, Brochures, n.d., 1986 (Box 8)
  - Houses in Northern Virginia: clippings, 1982-1996 (Box 8)
  - Alexander Hunter I: Deeds, Notes, Photographs, n.d., 1845 (Box 8)
  - Bushrod Hunter: Notes, Deeds, Wills, 1817-1887 (Box 8)
  - B.W. Hunter, Brookdale: Deeds, 1882-1921 (Box 9)
  - Fannie B. Hunter: Deeds, 1887-1941 (Box 9)
  - Louise Chapman Hunter: Notes (Box 9)
  - Hunter Family: Letter, Notes, Genealogies, 1988 (Box 9)
  - Hunter Family and its Connections with Arlington County: Notes, Clippings, Photographs (Box 9)
  - "Hunter Family and its Connection with Arlington County": Drafts and Published Version (Box 9)
  - Hunter-Corse-Ramey-Hume Families: Deeds, 1868-1902 (Box 9)
  - Arlington and Local Indians: Reports, Clippings, Notes, n.d., 1966-1994 (Box 9)
  - Jennings Properties, Inc.: Deeds, 1974-1988 (Box 9)
  - Claudius B. Jewell: Deeds, 1873-1900 (Box 9)
  - Johnson and Offord Properties: Legal Documents, 1879-1924 (Box 9)
  - Jones, Ashton C. and Ashton Heights: Notes, Deeds, Reports, Clippings, 1909-1982 (Box 9)
  - Kern Tract, Upton Park: Clippings, 1983-1993 (Box 9)
  - Samuel King and Addison Family Legal Documents, 1847-1910 (Box 10)
  - Laleger: Deeds, 1902-1933 (Box 10)
  - Lamborn, Robert: Notes, Deeds, 1893, 1902 (Box 10)
  - Robert E. Lee: Cards, Brochures, Clippings, 1965-1994 (Box 10)
  - Lee Family: Clippings, Deeds, n.d., 1825-1826 (Box 10)
  - Lee Gardens: Clippings, 1986-1989 (Box 10)
  - Lewis, Rosenthal, Strickland: Deeds, 1900, 1949-1984 (Box 10)
  - Libraries in Arlington: Clippings, Newsletters, 1986-1991 (Box 10)
  - Loudon County: Pamphlets, Slides, 1967-1982 (Box 10)
  - Loudon County: Clippings, 1970, 1978-1996 (1) (Box 10)
  - Loudon County: Clippings, 1970, 1978-1996 (2) (Box 10)
  - Luna Park: Legal Documents, 1907-1928 (Box 10)
  - Lyon Park, Frank Lyon, Lyon and Fitch: Legal Documents, 1885-1930 (1) (Box 11)
  - Lyon Park, Frank Lyon, Lyon and Fitch: Legal Documents, 1885-1930 (2) (Box 11)
  - Park in Lyon Park: Articles, Legal Documents, 1909-1930 (Box 11)
  - Park in Lyon Park: Articles, Photographs, 1980 (Box 11)
  - Lyon Park: Clippings, Newsletters, Brochures, Deed, 1938, 1990-1994 (Box 11)
  - Lyon Park Citizens Association Constitution and Bylaws, 1958 (Box 11)
  - Lyon Village: Legal Documents, 1847-1922 (Box 11)
  - Lyon Village: Clippings, 1986-1982 (Box 11)
  - Adam Lynn and George Wise: Legal Documents, 1810 (Box 11)
  - Maps of Northern Virginia (Box 11)
  - Maps of Virginia (Box 11)
  - Marcey Family: Clippings, Deeds, Notes, 1833-1879, 1974 (Box 11)
  - Mason, G. Grant, Jr.: Notes, Deeds, Photographs, Clippings, 1948-1969 (Box 11)
  - Maywood: Correspondence, Brochures, Deed, Clippings, 1946-1995 (Box 11)
  - McLean: Notes, Articles, Clippings, 1988-1993 (Box 11)
  - McLean History: "Old Roads and New Insights" by Winslow R. Hatch, 1985 (Box 11)
  - Minor Hill: Clippings, 1986-1990 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous Arlington County Source Materials (Box 11)
  - National Airport: Deeds, Letter, 1893-1943, 1986 (Box 12)
  - National Airport and Dulles Airport: Clippings, 1985-1996 (Box 12)
  - Nauck: Clippings, Deed, 1915, 1989-1994 (Box 12)
  - Navy Annex: Clippings, Brochure, 1984-1994 (Box 12)
  - Netherlands Carillon: Clippings, 1987-1995 (Box 12)
  - Newspapers in Northern Virginia: Clippings, 1978-1994 (Box 12)
  - Northern Virginia, Colonial Period: Notes, Reports, Clippings, n.d., 1906-1989 (Box 12)
  - Northern Virginia Localities: Miscellaneous Clippings, 1982-1994 (Box 12)
  - Northern Virginia Committee on Archives and History: Notes, Correspondence, 1992-1995 (Box 12)
  - Norton-King: 20 acres, Deeds, Notes, n.d., 1900-1901 (Box 12)
  - Palisades, Dawson, North Highlands, Woodmont: Clippings, 1987-1992 (Box 12)
  - Park Authority: Brochures, Clippings, Correspondence, Report, 1936-1994 (Box 12)
  - Pentagon and Pentagon City: Clippings, Article, Brochure, 1985-1993 (Box 12)
  - Personalities of Virginia: Newsletters, Brochures, 1985-1988 (Box 12)
  - Personalities of Virginia: Clippings, 1981-1993 (Box 12)
  - Piluso, Charles J.: Correspondence, Deed, Clippings, Notes, 1969-1976 (Box 12)
  - Potomac Overlook Park: Deeds, 1887-1966 (Box 13)
  - Potomac Overlook Park: Deeds, 1887-1966 (Box 13)
  - Potomac Overlook Park: Correspondence, 1968-1975 (Box 13)
  - Potomac Overlook Park History by Dorothea Abbott, 1988 (Box 13)
  - Potomac Overlook Park History by D. Abbott, Extra Copies (Box 13)
  - Potomac Overlook Park: Maps, Reports, Notes, Clippings, n.d., 1957, 1991 (Box 13)
  - Preservation and Restoration: Clippings, Brochures, 1986-1990 (Box 13)
  - Railroads in Arlington County: Legal Documents, 1895-1934 (Box 13)
  - Reitz, Lewis and Mary: Deeds, Clipping, 1916-1948 (Box 13)
  - A. Richards and Co. Suit, 1885-1982 (Box 13)
  - Ridge Road: Clippings, 1983-1988 (Box 13)
  - River Estates off Military Road: Clippings, 1990 (Box 13)
  - Roads: Notes, Clippings, 1988-1995 (Box 13)
  - Theodore Roosevelt Island: Notes, Clippings, Brochures, 1988 (Box 13)
  - Rosslyn: Photographs, Documents, 1895-1993 (Box 13)
  - Rosslyn: Clippings, 1985-1995 (Box 13)
  - Arlington Schools: Clippings, Deeds, Notes, Brochures, 1899, 1922, 1984-1994 (Box 14)
  - Shirlington and Fairlington: Clippings, 1986-1988 (Box 14)
  - Shosteck: Trails around Washington (Box 14)
  - Slave Cemeteries, 1996-1998 (Box 14)
  - St. John's Catholic Church: Pamphlets, Correspondence, Clipping, 1981-1998 (Box 14)
  - Stetson-Four Mile Run: Clippings (Box 14)
  - Summer Hill: Notes, Deed: "Arlington's Summer Hill Plantation," n.d., 1851-1938 (Box 14)
  - Summer Hill: Stewart, Martin, Raub: Deeds, 1871-1877 (Box 14)
  - Swann Family: Deeds, 1837-1904 (Box 14)
  - "The Land of Maria Syphax and the Abbey Mausoleum" by Dorothea Abbott, 1983 (Box 14)
  - Taylor Property: Deeds and Records, 1844-1927, 1990-1991 (Box 14)
  - Toxic Waste Sites in Virginia: Clipping, 1991 (Box 14)
  - John L. Tavers: Deeds, 1886-1915 (Box 14)
  - Travers Family and Cemetery: Deeds, 1832-1910 (Box 14)
  - Travers Family and Cemetery: Deeds, 1920-1992 (Box 14)
  - Travers Family and Cemetery: Correspondence, 1989-1991 (Box 14)
  - Travers Family and Cemetery: Notes, Clippings, Photos, n.d., 1989-1990 (Box 14)
  - Travers Family Genealogy: Notes, Photographs, Biography (Box 14)
  - Trees in Arlington: Clippings, 1986-1990 (Box 15)
  - Nicholas Trust and U.S. Involvement with Mexico: Notes (Box 15)
  - Trist Family: Article Drafts, Notes, Clippings, Transcripts, n.d., 1988 (Box 15)
  - "Virginia J. Trist" by Dorothea Abbott: Letter Copies, n.d., 1841 (Box 15)
  - U.S. Geological Survey Maps of Virginia, Maryland, and District of Columbia, 1987-1990 (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings re: Virginia and District of Columbia, 1994-1999 (Box 15)
  - Virginia Brick Company and Alfred Richards Brick Company, 1875-1900 (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous Notes on Virginia Families (Box 15)
  - Virginia Historical Society History and Biography, vol. 3: Clipping (Box 15)
  - Virginia Square: Clippings, 1983-1995 (Box 15)
  - Wardman, Harry: Deeds, 1916 (Box 15)
  - "Washington, a Chronological and Documentary History, 1790-1970 ." (Box 15)
  - Washington-Lee Shopping Center: Clippings, 1983-1986 (Box 15)
  - Watters Family: Notes, Clippings, Correspondence, 1892-1986 (Box 15)
  - Watters Family: Wills and Deeds, 1892-1998 (Box 15)
  - William Watters Foundation: Agendas, Minutes, 1998-1999 (Box 15)
  - William Watters Foundation: Newsletters, Correspondence, 1994-1999 (Box 15)
  - "Elephants and Quaker Guns" by Jane Chapman Whitt (Box 15)
  - "Recollections" by Josephine Cleary Wimsatt (Box 15)
  - Wren Family: Notes, Wills, Deeds, n.d., 1803-1889, 1998 (Box 15)
  - Writings, Miscellaneous, by Dorothea Abbott (Box 15)
- George and Martha Washington
  - Publications
    - Barons of the Potomack and the Rappahannock by Moncure D. Conway, 1892 (Box 16)
    - Colonial Williamsburg Official Guidebook, 1976 (Box 16)
    - The First Ladies by Margaret Brown Klapthor, 1989 (Box 16)
    - First Ladies: Political Role and Public Image by E.P. Mayo and D.D. Meringolo, 1994 (Box 16)
    - The Forming of a Nation (Box 16)
    - George Washington by Woodrow Wilson, 1903 (Box 16)
    - Martha Washington by LaVere Anderson, 1975 (Box 16)
    - Martha Washington: Our First Lady (Box 16)
    - Some American Ladies: Some Informal Biographies by Meade Menningerode. Chapter on Martha Washington (Box 16)
    - Vital Records of Three Burned Counties by Theresa Fisher, 1995 (Box 16)
    - Washington: A Biography (Box 16)
    - Washington and the American Republic by Benson J. Lossing, 1870 (Box 16)
    - Washington's Lady by E. Thane, 1960 (Box 17)
    - Williamsburg in Colonial Times (Box 17)
    - Wills of George Washington and his Immediate Ancestors, edited by W.C, Ford, 1891 (Box 17)
    - Women of the Colonial and Revolutionary Times, "Martha Washington" by Anne H. Wharton, 1897 (Box 17)
    - Worthy Partner: the Papers of Martha Washington compiled by Joseph E. Fields (Box 17)
  - Alphabetical Series
    - Arlington County: Notes, Clippings, n.d., 1973 (Box 17)
    - Brochures of Historic Sites (Box 17)
    - Bust of George Washington: Notes, Clippings, Correspondence, 1980 (Box 17)
    - Colonial Williamsburg, Autumn 1998 (Box 17)
    - G.W.P. Custis: Notes, Photocopies (Box 17)
    - Custis Family: Notes (Box 17)
    - William Dandridge, Elsing Green: Notes and Photocopies (Box 17)
    - Dandridge Family: Notes, Photocopies (Box 18)
    - Dandridge Family: Photographs, Negatives, Slides (Box 18)
    - Dandridge, Tenn.: Notes, Photocopies (Box 18)
    - Dandridge, Tenn.: Clippings, Postcards (Box 18)
    - Fairfax County: Articles and Clippings, 1971-1994 (Box 18)
    - Hampton, Va.: Notes, Photocopies (Box 18)
    - Homes of the Washingtons (Box 18)
    - Mount Vernon: Notes and Clippings (Box 18)
    - New Kent Co., Va. and St. Peter's Parish: Notes, Pamphlets, Photocopies (Box 18)
    - Research Trip Expenses (Box 18)
    - Revolutionary War: Clippings, 1976-1991 (Box 18)
    - Stafford Co., Va.: Notes (Box 18)
    - George Washington: Miscellaneous Clippings, 1976-1998 (Box 18)
    - Notes, Photocopies, and Clippings re: George and Martha Washington (Box 18)
    - Photocopies and Notes re: Martha Washington (Box 18)
    - Clippings re: Martha Washington, 1982-1995 (Box 18)
    - Post cards of Washingtons, Mt. Vernon, Woodlawn, etc. (Box 18)
- Virginia Counties and Localities
  - Accomack-Chincoteague-Assateague: Clippings, 1989 (Box 19)
  - Albemarle County: Brochures (Box 19)
  - Albemarle County: Clippings, 1974-1994 (Box 19)
  - Amelia County and Augusta County: Clippings and Brochures (Box 19)
  - Bath County: Clipping, 1974 (Box 19)
  - Bedford County: Photographs, Clippings, Brochures, 1990-1994 (Box 19)
  - Botetourt County: Clippings, Brochures, 1981 (Box 19)
  - Campbell County and Chesterfield County: Brochures (Box 19)
  - Charles City County: Clippings, Brochures, 1969-1990 (Box 19)
  - Clarke County: Brochures, Comprehensive Plan, Clippings, 1974-1992 (Box 19)
  - Culpepper County: Clippings, 1984-1993 (Box 19)
  - Essex County: Clippings, Brochures, 1982 (Box 19)
  - Fauquier County: Clippings, Brochures, 1978-1996 (Box 19)
  - Fluvanna County: Clipping, 1993 (Box 19)
  - Franklin County: Clipping, Brochure, 1993 (Box 19)
  - Frederick County: Clippings and Brochures, 1974-1994 (Box 19)
  - Galax: Clipping, Brochures, 1988 (Box 19)
  - Gloucester County: Clippings, 1981-1996 (Box 19)
  - Goochland: Clipping, 1987 (Box 19)
  - Hampton, Norfolk, Newport News: Clippings and Brochures, 1982-1998 (Box 19)
  - Hanover County: Clipping, Brochure (Box 19)
  - Henrico County and Richmond: Clippings, Post Cards and Brochures, 1975-1996 (Box 19)
  - Henry County: Brochures (Box 20)
  - Isle of Wight County: Clipping, Brochures (Box 20)
  - James City County: Brochures (Box 20)